# Alex Preciado

# **SKILLS**

Quantum Software Development Manager with 8+ years of experience in developing predictive models, data infrastructure, and software for industry and international scientific collaborations. Core developer of the software used to model the <u>first image of a black hole</u> obtained by the EHT Collaboration. Currently leading the Core team developing <u>PennyLane</u>, Xanadu's open-source library for quantum computing and quantum machine learning. Also serving as an AI and Data Analytics Instructor at Schulich School of Business, York University.

- **Programming Languages:** Python, C++, shell scripting, prior experience with Fortran.
- Data Infrastructure. Proficient in AWS, GitHub, Databricks, Docker, Airflow, Tableau, Vault Enterprise.
- Database Management: MySQL, Postgres and Microsoft SQL servers. Cloudera Impala Data Warehouses.
- **High Performance Computing.** 2.5 years of experience developing parallelized software for HPC systems.
- Teaching: Expertise in delivering engaging content and designing course materials for AI & data analytics courses.

### **EXPERIENCE**

# Manager, Quantum Software Development

June 2023 – Present

Xanadu Quantum Technologies Inc.

- Lead the Core and High-Performance Computing teams in developing PennyLane, our cutting-edge Python library for quantum machine learning and quantum computing.
- Coordinate the development of CPU and GPU-based backends to simulate quantum hardware.
- Oversee the software development lifecycle for PennyLane.
- Facilitating team processes (iteration planning, technical roadmap definition, code discussions, bug tracking, and successful product delivery).
- Responsible for end-to-end people management.

# Manager, Machine Learning & Data Engineering

Aug 2021 - May 2023

HelloFresh Canada

- Led a team of 4 data engineers to support strategic partners across various business functions, including Demand Planning, Procurement, Production, Marketing, Product, Finance, HR.
- Coordinated the development of data products and data ingestion pipelines to support decision making and automation of business-critical processes.
- Managed the development of software solutions for demand planning, production scheduling and inventory management for the new ready-to-eat/ready-to-heat brand in Canada (Factor).
- Led the onboarding and implementation of new data infrastructure for the Canadian Data Team (AWS, Databricks, Airflow, Presto, Vault Enterprise, etc.).
- Managed Operational Databases to store Menu, Recipe, Supplier, Ingredient, QA & Inventory data.

Data Scientist Aug 2019 - July 2021

HelloFresh Canada

- Developed Market Share models and conducted Competitor Analysis using third party (credit card and website traffic) data for local and global leadership and Investors Relations teams.
- Customer 360. Led the creation of customer-level datasets for RFM analyses, customer segmentation, and Machine Learning models to identify high/mid/low-value customers.
- Built demand forecasting models to support aggressive add-on offer expansion during COVID-19 pandemic.
- Contributed to working groups on Data Literacy, Data Governance & Data Infrastructure. Served as Data Literacy coordinator to develop up-skilling frameworks & organize international Data Literacy campaigns.

## **Postdoctoral Researcher**

Nov 2016 - Jan 2019

Perimeter Institute for Theoretical Physics (Waterloo, ON)

- Led the development of the official parameter estimation library for the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) Collaboration, enabling the analysis of astrophysical data that resulted in the first image of a black hole.
- Devised and implemented parameterized models to estimate black hole parameters.
- Validated and tested analytical & numerical models using High-Performance Computing (HPC) systems.

### **TEACHING EXPERIENCE**

#### **Part-time Instructor**

Sep 2022 - Present

Schulich School of Business, York University

- Instructing AI and Data Analytics courses in the Master of Management in Artificial Intelligence (MMAI) and Master of Business Analytics (MBAN) programs.
- Courses taught: Database Fundamentals

# **Physics Instructor**

Apr 2011 - June 2013

Colegio Británico, Mexico

- Developed and delivered curriculum for High School Physics Courses
- Courses taught: Physics I & II, Selected Topic in Physics I & II

# **English Teacher**

Dec 2004 - June 2008

Harmon Hall, Mexico

- Developed and delivered curriculum for English language Courses
- Courses taught: Various Basic, Intermediate and Advanced English courses

# **EDUCATION**

PhD, Physics	University of Guanajuato (Mexico)	2010 - 2015
Masters, Physics	University of Guanajuato (Mexico)	2008 - 2010
B. Eng., Electrical Engineering	University of Guanajuato (Mexico)	2002 - 2008

# **AWARDS & ACHIEVEMENTS**

- Albert Einstein Medal for the first image of a supermassive black hole (May 2020).
- 2020 Breakthrough Prize in Fundamental Physics for the 1st image of a supermassive black hole (Nov 2019).
- **Diamond Achievement Award of the National Science Foundation**, presented to the team that captured the first-ever image of a black hole (May 2019).
- **Bronze Medal**, VII Ibero-American Physics Olympiad (2002).
- Gold Medal, XII National Physics Olympiad (Mexico, 2001).

#### **MAIN PUBLICATIONS**

Quantum Cosmology and Alternative Gravity Theories:

- Well-posed Cauchy formulation for Einstein-æther theory, Classical and Quantum Gravity, 36 (2019), No. 16.
- Quantum cosmology in Hořava-Lifshitz gravity, Phys Rev. D 86, 063502 (2012).
- A quantum cosmological model in Hořava-Lifshitz gravity, AIP Conference Proceedings 1396, 151 (2011).

Publications with the Event Horizon Telescope (EHT) Collaboration:

- THEMIS: A Parameter Estimation Framework for the Event Horizon Telescope, ApJ Letters, 897 (2020) 139.
- Spacetime Tomography Using the Event Horizon Telescope, ApJ Letters, 892 (2020) 132.
- The EHT General Relativistic Magnetohydrodynamic Code Comparison Project, ApJS, 243 (2019) 26.
- EHT observations of the jet launching and collimation in Centaurus A, Nature Astronomy, 5 (2021) 1017-1028.

First Sgr A\* EHT Results (The First Image of the Black Hole in the Center of our Galaxy):

- I. The Shadow of the Supermassive Black Hole in the Center of the Milky Way, ApJ Letters, 930 (2022) L12.
- II. EHT and Multiwavelength Observations, Data Processing, and Calibration, ApJ Letters, 930 (2022) L13.
- III. Imaging of the Galactic Center Supermassive Black Hole, ApJ Letters, 930 (2022) L14.
- IV. Variability, Morphology, and Black Hole Mass, ApJ Letters, 930 (2022) L15.
- <u>V. Testing Astrophysical Models of the Galactic Center Black Hole</u>, *ApJ Letters*, 930 (2022) L16.
- VI. Testing the Black Hole Metric, ApJ Letters, 930 (2022) L17.

First M87 EHT Results (The First Image of the Black Hole in the Center of the M87 Galaxy):

- I. The Shadow of the Supermassive Black Hole, ApJ Letters, 875 (2019) Li.
- II. Array and Instrumentation, ApJ Letters, 875 (2019) L2.
- III. Data Processing and Calibration, ApJ Letters, 875 (2019) L3.
- IV. Imaging the Central Supermassive Black Hole, ApJ Letters, 875 (2019) L4.
- <u>V. Physical Origin of the Asymmetric Ring</u>, *ApJ Letters*, 875 (2019) L5.
- VI. The Shadow and Mass of the Central Black Hole, ApJ Letters, 875 (2019) L6.
- <u>VII. Polarization of the Ring</u>, *ApJ Letters*, 910 (2021) L12.
- VIII. Magnetic Field Structure near The Event Horizon, ApJ Letters, 910 (2021) L13.
- X. Detection of Near-horizon Circular Polarization, ApJ Letters, 957 (2023) L20

**Note:** A full List of publications can be found in INSPIRE (<a href="here">here</a>) and Google Scholar (<a href="here">here</a>).